Hello and welcome to the second video in the
"Getting to grips with Monero" series.
In this video we'll be developing our understanding
of nodes; the most important piece of infrastructure
in the Monero ecosystem.
We'll be discussing what they are, why they're
important and demonstrating step-by-step
how to set up your own, so let's get going!
Fundamentally a Monero node is a piece of
hardware connected to the Internet which both
stores a copy of the blockchain and runs the
Monero software.
Running your own node and connecting to the
P2P network is kind of like downloading and
seeding a torrent for all those who want to
access it.
Nodes are programmed to follow a certain set
of rules which facilitate the running of the network.
An important abstraction from these rules
is the consensus mechanism.
It's through this mechanism that the legitimate
history of the Monero blockhain is maintained.
The greater the number of nodes in the network,
the more resilient it is against both
denial of service attacks and network partitioning.
Nodes are typically separated into two categories,
local and remote.
Local nodes are those **within** your local
network
Remote nodes are those **outside** your local
There are a few benefits to running a local
node, the most notable of which is privacy!
When you connect to remote nodes, it's possible
for the host to obtain the following details about you:
Your IP address
The block height from which your wallet started
synchronisation
The transaction IDs you broadcast and a list
of decoys
Depending on your privacy concerns, this might
not be ideal.
So make sure you connect to a remote node
hosted by someone you can trust.
This is very important!
If you're unable to run your own node for
whatever reason, you can skip over this video for now.
Another thing to think about, either when
connecting to remote nodes or hosting your
own, is that your Internet Service Provider
(ISP) will be able to recognise all of your activities.
Although this information doesn't deanonymise
your Monero address or transactions, it can
still be used by malicious actors.
Hosting your own node for use with your own
wallet simply reduces the amount of your personal
data floating around the web.
Monero's Dandelion++ technology does the hard
part by seamlessly obfuscating the origin
of all transactions.
This article from the good folks at LocalMonero
goes into more detail about Dandelion++.
Before we continue, you need to learn about
whatever local risks, if any, are associated
with hosting your own node.
This is important for your personal security
and obviously depends on where in the world
you live and work.
Currently, the best ways to shield your Internet
activities from malicious actors is through
either a trustworthy Virtual Proxy Network
(VPN), Tor routing (The Onion Routing Project)
or Invisible Internet Project (I2P).
Best practices are not timeless and there
will always be developments in the web and
the Monero ecosystem, but the Monero developer
community is one of the largest and most privacy-focused
organizations in this space.
Please skip to the next video if you have
any security concerns.
If you still want to host your own node and
support the network, we will of course be
showing you how to do so with a VPN in Video
4 of this series: Using Monero with Enhanced Privacy.
Running your node 24/7 is of most benefit
to the Monero network and for most, it's not
practical or environmentally friendly to run
nodes on powerful and inefficient machines.
It's for this reason we'd recommend the use
of low powered, efficient architechture like
the "system on a chip" (SOC) designs from
AMD and Intel.
Generally speaking the Rasberry Pi and other
ARM-based (Advanced RISC Machine) systems
would be ideal for something like this.
However, it's in fact not the best platform
for running the Monero daemon.
This is because the hardware lacks support
for the "Advanced Encryption Standard" (AES) instruction set.
The major dissadvantage is drastically longer
sync times.
Typically, only systems with x86 architecture
will benefit from this instruction set.
The Monero daemon requires 1 to 2 GB of memory
to run, so aim to use a system with at least
4 GB of memory.
If you're planning on using a single board
computer like the Raspberry Pi and are feeling
adventurous, we would recommend this guide
published by
the good folk from the monero-ecosystem work-group.
Be aware that there may be a more up to date
version when you watch this video.
The software required to run a node can be
found on the official github repository, the
link for which can be found in the video description.
If you followed all of the steps from our
other video, 'importing public keys and verifying
hashes', you should have already downloaded
and verified these files.
If you haven't, please make sure you do that
now.
You'll find it in the playlist labelled "Getting
to grips with Monero".
The next sections will cover the process for
Linux and Windows independently, please use
the time stamps below to get to the part that
suits you.
If you're using a linux distro like I am currently,
then you're going to need to open a command
line terminal.
I'm going to navigate to the right directory
using the terminal and the change directory
command: `cd`.
You can then use `ls` to check you're in the
right place.
If you're using the file explorer, head to
the proper folder and *Right click* and select
*Open in Terminal*.
You'll find the commands used in the description
below, feel free to copy and paste them into
your terminal window.
To paste into the terminal window you'll need
to use the *Shift* key in addition to *Ctrl*.
Copy - *Ctrl + Shift + C*
Paste - *Ctrl + Shift + V*
We'll be using the following command for the
next step;
Let's break this down.
First, we're making a directory called *monerod*,
in the user's directory (`/home/"USERNAME"`),
then we're using the `tar` function to unpack
the compressed folder into the directory we
just created.
Now, let's run that by hitting *Enter*
Use the `cd` command and navigate to the newly
created directory and look for the extracted
folder using the `ls` command
The first thing we're going to do is move
the downloaded file to a custom folder.
First select and cut using *Ctrl + X*
Next we'll go to the `C:` drive to create
a folder called *monerod*.
Double click on the new folder and paste the
zip file you just cut with *Ctrl + V*
Double click the zip file to open, then drag
and drop the folder into the address bar,
onto the name of the parent folder.
Open the *monerod* folder when finished.
As Windows users it's best to add a custom
security rule to your virus and threat protection
settings to avoid any complications when running
your node:
First, open the virus and threat protection
settings by typing in the search bar or opening
the start menu and typing in `virus`
Next, under *Virus and Threat Protection Settings*,
click on *Manage Settings*
Scroll down until you see the *Exclusions*
section and choose *Add or remove exclusions*
Click *Add an exclusion*
Choose *Folder*
Then select the folder that you just created
in the root directory
Creating a config file is a pretty simple
way to tailor the Monero daemon to suit your
own needs and circumstances.
There is no default config file, so we'll
be doing this from scratch using the documents
hosted on monerodocs.org as a reference.
In the monerod folder create a file called
**bitmonero.conf**, this can be created, opened
and edited with any text editor so we won't
be covering OS specific details here.
We're going to use the example file from the
Monero docs website as a template to work from.
Please click on the subheading **Examples**
and copy the example to your clipboard using
the provided button.
Now paste it into your text editor.
You'll notice quite a few **#** symbols in
this text.
These are comments.
Every time the Monero daemon comes across
one, it ignores it and skips to the next line.
It's a really easy way for us to leave information
and comments in the file without them interfering
with its operation.
There are a lot of different settings you
can apply to the daemon and the MoneroDocs
web page is a great resource for finding the
things you want.
The first option we see here enables us to
set the location of the blockchain.
This requires a little thought because the
database that contains the monero blockchain
is rather large, and ever-growing.
One of the prerequisites for this video was
at least 50GB of disk space, this is the minimum
required space and would only allow you to
download a pruned version of the blockchain,
not the entire thing.
Simply put; a pruned node is one with the
entire transaction history, but only a small
share of the details.
Not all pruned nodes are created equal, only
together can they preserve the whole blockchain
as each holds about 1/8^(th) of the required
detail.
Pruned nodes are always recommended over using
remote ones, however if you have the space
it's a big help for the network if you host
a full node.
A full node would require around 130GB currently,
but this size is always increasing.
To set the location of the blockchain you
need to edit everything after the **=** sign.
Make sure you include the full directory path,
including the drive letter if you're using windows.
I'm going to leave it as default for now.
If you want to download a pruned copy of the
blockchain we need to add a few more lines,
first I'm going to add a subheading starting
with **#** called Custom, this way i remember
that I added the following lines myself.
Underneath we're going to add `sync-pruned-blocks=1`
and `prune-blockchain=1`.
The value **1** indicates we want to enable
this option.
If you want to disable them, you can either
add a **#** to the start of the line to comment
it out or change **1** to **0**.
Before we take a look at the rest of the file,
we're going to add two more lines to our custom
list; `enable-dns-blocklist=1` and `no-zmq=1`.
Enabling the block list prevents connections
to known bad actors and is centrally maintained
by the Monero core team.
The `no-zmq` option disables a particular
interface we will not be using, limiting the
potential attack surface.
Let's move onto the default config.
The first setting here sets the location of
the database, which will be created to store
the blockchain data.
I'm going to set it so that it saves it to
a new folder called *data* within the *monerod*
folder we created earlier.
To do this we can simply replace this location
with *data*.
The next thing on the list is the location
we want the Monero daemon to save logs.
I'm going to change this to the same **data**
folder by replacing everything that comes
before *monerod.log* with *data/logs/*.
If anything goes wrong, we can quickly and
easily investigate from here!
Before continuing, let's consider whats actually
going on here when the node is spinning up.
Every time you start the Monero daemon it
starts several processes which use different
ports to run, one of which is the P2P service.
This is how your node communicates with the
rest of the network and keeps itself up-to-date.
Currently the IP address is bound to **`0.0.0.0`**,
this is the best option if you haven't got
any kind of custom networking.
The port number is bound to the default recommendation.
You can of course change this to what ever
you like, but be mindful that a wide variety
of ports are used by other applications/services,
so it's a good idea to stick to the recommended ones.
Being able to change this port number is great
if you cannot forward a certain port on your
router or if your VPN service requires a certain
value
However for now, leave this port as default.
For our node to be a fully-fledged member
of the Monero network we need to
***forward this port on both our firewall and router***
so that our node can shake hands with other nodes.
The other process on the list is the Monero
RPC, or Remote Prcedure Call.
RPC is the method used for communication between
wallets and nodes.
We're not going to go into too much detail
in this video, but it is possible for you
to allow external connections.
Running an RPC service is certainly helpful
for those who don't run their own node, but
it exposes an entirely different part of the
Monero codebase to the internet.
As many of you will be setting this up on
your own personal computer, we advise against
this for now.
To save time in this video we're going to
skip over the next two sections in the config
file.
If you're interested in what they do, please
check out MoneroDocs for more info.
Finally we move onto network traffic.
How many peers you connect to and the bandwidth
you allocate is totally customisable.
Increasing the outpeers and the down rate
will directly contribute to your initial sync.
I suggest you have these pretty high to begin
with, you can always change things later on
to suit your circumstances.
I'm going to leave all of this as default
for now.
The next thing we're going to want to do is
change the location of the monerod program.
You can do this through the file explorer
or terminal, it's up to you.
You need to be sure that either the monerod
binary or monerod.exe is now located in the
"monerod" folder alongside the config.
Each time you download an updated copy of
the software, you will need to replace this file.
After all our work we can start our node for
the very first time.
Using the terminal, navigate to the folder
that the monderod program is located in, then:
**for Windows:**
`shift+right click`
open up a powershell
type `./monerod.exe --config-file=./bitmonero.conf`
**for Linux:**
`right-click`
open a terminal
type `./monerod --config-file=./bitmonero.conf`
Now let's hit enter!
As you can see from the messages, we're now
syncing the blockchain to your computer.
This is a pretty lengthy process so be prepared.
You can take a break from it whenever you
like by using the command *Ctrl + C* to cancel
the operation.
To start it again from where you left off,
simply follow the same process.
Currently we're only leaching the blockchain
from the P2P network and sharing is caring
after all, so we'll want to enable seeding
as well.
To do this, we're going to have to set special
rules in the firewall to allow incoming connections
for the p2p port (18080) on both our computers
and routers.
This may or may not be technically possible
for you.
This will all depend on your ISP and aministrative
access to your router.
The following two sections will cover linux
and windows independently, so please head
to the appropriate section.
As for routers, please take a look at your
manufacturers recommendations.
If you're currently using a VPN, please take
a look at our video **Using Monero With Enhanced Privacy**
as things will be a little bit different
for you.
Forwarding the required port is relatively
simple as a linux user.
To do so, we're going to use the **Uncomplicated
Firewall**, ufw for short.
This may be entirely new to you and if it
is, you will first want to see if it's installed.
Open up a new terminal and enter `ufw --version`.
If you don't get a printout with a version
number you'll need to install it, which you
can do via your package manager.
Now let's enter these three commands:
With this command we're going to Enable the ufw
Then, block incoming connections
and finally, allow all outgoing connections
The current state of our firewall isn't ideal
right now as we won't be able to use our browsers
or download system updates.
For this reason we're going to want to allow
ports 443 (tcp-https) and 80 (tcp-http).
To do this we're going to run the following
commands:
Now that the ufw has been enabled and your
firewall has been hardened, your computer
is a little more secure and we're ready to
make an exception for the Monero daemon:
This command will allow traffic to access
your monero daemon, you may remember this
port number from the config file we created
earlier.
After you press enter you should see "rule
added."
To double check that it worked, you can run
`sudo ufw status`.
We can see it listed in the print out, so
everything went fine.
Well, that's all there is to it for your PC.
The only thing left to do is forward the port
on your router.
Every router is different, so please have
a look at your manufacturer's instructions for this step.
To begin, click on the Windows start menu
and type `firewall`.
Click on the result from Windows defender.
Once open, head to advanced settings and choose
inbound rules in the left hand column.
Next select *New rule* under the *actions*
subheading.
Here we need to select *Port* and then *Next*.
The protocol we're interested in is *tcp*
and now we need to specify the port used by
the Monero daemon which is **`18080`**
In the next menu, we want to select *Allow
the connection*.
Now it's time to name the rule *Monerod P2P*
before clicking the *Finish" button.
That's it, we've opened up our port in Windows
for the Monero daemon to communicate with
the rest of the network.
The only thing left to do is forward the port
on your router.
Every router is different, so please have
a look at your manufacturers instructions for this step.
On a 100Mbit connection and writing to an
ssd, it's taken me a little over a day to
sync the entire blockchain.
Once it's synced you should see the message
**SYNCHRONISED OK**.
We can confirm the status of our nodes by
using the command `status`.
This shows the height of the blockchain and
a few other bits, including the number of
incoming and outgoing connections.
You will notice that I curently have no *in*
connections, this is because I'm yet forwarded
this port on my router.
Another neat command is `print_net_stats`
which lets us see how much data has been received
and contributed to the network and at what
rate.
Of course no internet connection is the same
and you may want to limit your traffic.
You can do so on the fly or by editing the
config file we set up earlier.
It may take some time for you to find the
settings that really suit you.
If you're interested in seeing what else you
can do whilst the daemon is running type `help`.
As the initial sync is complete, I'm going
to limit my traffic.
I'm going to offer 1 MB/s to my incoming connections
and 1.5MB/s to outgoing as I use my PC for
many other things.
I'm going to do so using the commands `limit_up`
and `limit_down`.
Once again, please take a look at MoneroDocs
for more documentation.
It has lots of useful information and will
help you to tune your node!
Well, there we have it, our very own node!
Now we can rest easy knowing that we're supporting
the network and have the basis for all our
future monero needs!
If you have any comments or questions, feel
free to leave them below, but please search
for similar questions before doing so.
That's it for this video, if you're interested
in seeing how you can put your node to use,
you can check out the other videos in this
series.
Thanks for watching and bye for now.
~moneroguides